(upbeat music)
- Hello, everyone, and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine,
and today we're going
to continue in our series
about job interviews.
- That's right, and on this occasion,
we're taking a look at part
five, our interview series,
where we explain why
we left our previous job.
- Okay, and so in an interview,
this is a very popular question.
Why did you leave your last job?
Learn some tools for
answering this question
and today's dialogue,
we're going to take a
listen to it first, and we'll
be back in a moment.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, now I'd like to find
out more about your last job.
- I see you spent almost four
years at the London weekly.
Is that right?
- Yes, that's right.
To be honest, the first
year was quite tough for me.
I was really just treated
more like an intern.
I didn't have many responsibilities,
and I found it quite frustrating.
- So, what changed?
- Well, slowly but surely I
proved myself, and the new
editor liked me, so he
promoted me to features writer.
- Wow, a real step up.
- Yes, I was responsible for
restaurant and food reviews, mostly.
I spent three years in that position.
But to be honest, it wasn't an area of
journalism I wanted to stay in long term.
- I see, so why did you
decide to leave, finally?
- I just felt that the paper couldn't
offer me any new opportunities.
I really needed a more
challenging role to be honest.
(upbeat music)
- All right, we're back, and
as we saw Rebecca handled it
quite well explaining
why you left your last job,
because obviously you don't
wanna say something like,
"Well, I just really
didn't like my company,"
or, you know, the boss
was a really bad guy.
- Or I was fired for being lazy.
- Exactly, so why don't we take a look
at a couple of different
words on language takeaway?
- Language takeaway.
Okay, so we've got some
great descriptive words here.
These are some adjectives.
The first one is tough.
So, Rebecca said, to be honest,
the first year was quite tough for me.
- All right, so she's
describing that her first year
at that company where she was working, it
was tough, and that means hard, difficult.
- That's right, so you could say,
this is a really tough situation.
I mean, it's a difficult situation.
It's hard because there's no easy answer.
- Exactly, so if you describe something as
tough, it means that it's very difficult.
Now, there is another meaning to this where
it can be that you are a strong person.
- Right, so that's different because we're
talking about a person, not a situation,
but if you're talking about
a job or an experience,
or even homework, like this homework is
really tough, it means that it's very hard.
- Exactly.
Well, apart from her job
of being a little bit tough,
she said that it was
also a little bit frustrating.
- Okay, so usually
these things go together.
If something is tough, like it's
difficult, it's usually frustrating too.
And so in this case,
something is frustrating
when it makes you unhappy, or for
example, it makes you feel stressed.
So something that's
frustrating is not a good thing.
- Exactly, so as you gave the example
with the homework assignment,
if you have maybe a math
assignment that's very difficult
and you can't solve it,
you don't find the solution,
then you get frustrated, you
get maybe angry at yourself
or you get very angry for
not being able to solve it.
So that's when it's
something is frustrating.
- I hate being frustrated.
(laughing)
- Exactly, well, it's not a nice feeling,
but she said that,
well, it was frustrating,
it was tough, but after
a while, I proved myself.
- Okay, so that means that
she was able to show someone
that she can handle difficult things,
difficult work, difficult situations.
And so she said, I proved myself
and the new editor liked me.
So basically, she did a really good job.
- Exactly, so if you prove yourself,
you're showing someone
that you have great ability
or capabilities of solving a problem
or being able to handle a difficult job.
- That's right, for example, I could say,
last year, Bob didn't do very well at school,
but this year he really proved himself.
He studied hard and he
got really good grades.
- Exactly, and well, Rebecca,
what she got in exchange
for proving herself, she got promoted.
- This is great, so
promotions are good things.
The verb here is to
promote or to be promoted.
So in this case, she was promoted.
You could say last year, I was promoted
or he will be promoted next
week, he doesn't know yet.
- Exactly, now remember
that to be promoted
means to get a better
position in your job.
Now, as we mentioned,
the verb is to promote
and you may be asking
yourself why you're
using the verb to be in
the past was promoted.
And this is because it's an ED adjective.
It's an adjective that's ends in ED.
So you may think it's a verb,
but it's actually an adjective.
- The verb here is to be.
- Exactly, so I was promoted.
Was is obviously our
verb here, the verb to be,
but promoted is an
adjective that ends in ED.
- Okay, and so if I'm the boss, the action
I do, the verb I do is I promote someone.
So this can be a little bit tricky, but we
recommend that you check out the website
for more details because we have
lots of examples of how to use this.
- Exactly, well, she got
promoted and well, she was really
happy for a while, but then
she said, you know what?
I really needed a more challenging
role, a more challenging job.
- Okay, challenging is a great adjective.
It means something is difficult,
or it gives you a challenge.
So that means it's not easy.
- Yeah, so she found that
her job was a little bit too easy,
so she wanted something
a little bit more challenging.
- Okay, and so this is a really great
word for job interviews in particular,
because you're basically
saying, I want hard work.
I want to prove myself
that we go again, proof.
I want to show you that I'm a
good employee or a hard worker,
and so I want a challenge,
something that's hard.
- Exactly, so something
that is hard is a
challenge, or you want
something challenging.
So why don't we review these
words that we've taken a look at now.
Let's go back to the
dialogue and listen to it again.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, now I'd like to find
out more about your last job.
I see you spent almost four
years at the London Weekly.
Is that right?
- Yes, that's right.
To be honest, the first
year was quite tough for me.
I was really just treated
more like an intern.
I didn't have many responsibilities,
and I found it quite frustrating.
- So what changed?
- Well, slowly but surely I
proved myself, and the new
editor liked me, so he
promoted me to features writer.
- Wow, a real step up.
- Yes, I was responsible for
restaurant and food reviews,
mostly, I spent three
years in that position.
But to be honest, it wasn't an area of
journalism I wanted to stay in long term.
- I see, so why did you
decide to leave finally?
- I just felt that the paper couldn't
offer me any new opportunities.
I really needed a more
challenging role, to be honest.
- All right, we're back,
so now let's take a look
at a couple of phrases we've
picked out for you on Fluency Builder.
- Fluency Builder.
- Okay, this first phrase is unusual
because it actually happens
at the end of sentences.
This is very, very common with people
who are making small talk
or who are doing interviews.
This is the phrase, is that right?
- So basically, you
saw that in the first line,
Mr. Parsons was talking to her and said,
"Well, I see you spent almost four years
"at the London
weekly, is that right?
" So he's ending the
sentence with this phrase.
- So he's making the sentence a question.
I see that you did this, is that right?
So he's asking her to confirm
the fact that he knows about her,
because maybe they've
never really talked before.
So this is a good way for him
to ask her to give more details.
- Exactly.
- So for example, Marco, I hear
that you're from Ecuador, is that right?
- That's right, so apart
from ending the sentence
like this, if maybe somebody
asks you, is that right?
You have to confirm, you have
to say, yes, that's right, or yes.
- It's also good to elaborate, to give
more details, so yes, I'm from Ecuador.
I was born there, but I've
lived in the United States.
- This is a way to give more information,
because that's basically
what the person's asking.
- Yeah, I think it wouldn't be very good
if you read a job interview,
and the person says, is that right?
And you say, yes, that's right.
And then you don't say anything else.
- So yeah, basically the
point is you have to confirm,
or deny it to say, yes, that's
right, or no, that's not right.
And then you have to give some
information about the question.
- Exactly.
All right, now moving
on, when Rebecca again,
was talking about her job,
she was saying it's tough,
and I didn't have many responsibilities,
and I found it quite frustrating.
- Okay, so this is like lost and found,
like I lost my hat, and I found it later.
No, no, this is what's
interesting about this verb, find.
We are not actually looking for something,
or we didn't actually find
something we were looking for.
This is kind of a realization, right?
- That's right, it's like a feeling.
So I find this movie boring.
That means I think this movie is boring.
It's the way that you're
thinking about something.
- That's right, or you can say, oh, I
found Paris to be quite an expensive city.
- Yeah, pretty expensive.
- So this is your impression.
This is the way that you
feel about something.
- Exactly.
So this is another way that
you can use this word to find.
Now again, when Rebecca talked about proving
herself, she used a very interesting,
I would say phrase, a very popular
well-known phrase, slowly but surely.
- Okay, so slowly but surely
is the opposite of right away.
So something that happens
right away is immediate.
I got promoted right away.
But slowly but surely
means after lots of time
and even hard work,
this good thing happened.
Or it's usually a good thing actually.
- Yeah, it's, you're basically
saying that you didn't
do anything very quickly,
but you did it very well.
So slowly but surely, I
finished building my home.
- Right, so it didn't happen
overnight, but it did happen over time.
You can also say this
about studying a language.
You know, at the beginning
learning English was
really hard, but slowly
but surely I became fluent.
- Exactly, okay, so slowly but surely.
And the last phrase that
we have for you today,
you may have seen that
Rebecca used this phrase
to be honest a couple of times
before explaining something.
So why does she say to be honest?
- To be honest is sometimes
something we say in English
to fill some space or
some time, we call it filler,
but it's also a way to introduce
something that's negative.
So for example, in this dialogue she's
talking about her negative experiences.
You know, my job was
tough, my experience was bad.
So she says to be honest, it wasn't
the best experience, but I learned from it.
She's saying this to introduce some things
that are maybe not
positive, not happy things.
- That's right, so it's another way of
saying, look, I'm going to tell you the truth.
It may not be something positive,
but you know, this is what happened.
So to be honest, I didn't really like
my last employer or something like that.
- Right, well you can even
talk about this with your friends.
So hey, Marco, did you like
that movie, Shutter Island?
- To be honest, I didn't really see it.
- Oh, fell asleep.
(laughing)
- Or you could say to
be honest, I didn't love it.
- I didn't really like it.
- Exactly, so it's a very good phrase,
but don't overuse it.
I think sometimes you get into the habit
of using it all the time
and just like, like, you know.
- Yes.
- Well, you know, like I went to
the movies like yesterday, like, and--
- Like to be honest,
like, so try to keep these
fillers as you describe
them to a minimum.
So don't really use them too much.
- Yes, say thoughts and
ideas, nice action verbs,
not too much fillers because
sometimes, especially in an interview,
it makes people think that you
don't really know much to say.
- Yeah, exactly, okay.
So let's listen to the
dialogue for the last time
and we'll be back to
chat a little bit more.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, now I'd like to find
out more about your last job.
I see you spent almost four
years at the London Weekly.
Is that right?
- Yes, that's right.
To be honest, the first
year was quite tough for me.
I was really just treated
more like an intern.
I didn't have many responsibilities
and I found it quite frustrating.
- So what changed?
- Well, slowly but surely I
proved myself and the new
editor liked me so he
promoted me to features writer.
- Wow, a real step up.
- Yes, I was responsible for
restaurant and food reviews mostly.
I spent three years in that position.
But to be honest, it wasn't an area of
journalism I wanted to stay in long term.
- I see, so why did you
decide to leave finally?
- I just felt that the paper couldn't
offer me any new opportunities.
I really needed a more
challenging role to be honest.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so talking about your last
employer, this is a pretty ideal thing.
Now, do you have any
advice that you can give
our listeners about
describing your last job?
Why did you leave your previous employer?
- Well, I do have a little
bit of basic job advice.
I would say don't complain
about your last employer.
Don't say my boss was
mean, my co-workers were lazy,
my company was terrible
because usually as a person
doing an interview, that
makes you think that this person,
if they work for you,
will complain about you.
And so I think it's
important like what Rebecca
does in this dialogue
to keep it positive.
Every negative situation can
become a positive experience.
So the job was tough, but it
was a good challenge, right?
Or but she learned how
to do any new things.
- Exactly.
- I think this is important
for anybody in any language,
but in English, especially
to use some of these phrases
and to say, you know,
I really like a challenge
or I didn't feel this was
challenging enough,
things like this, as opposed
to my old boss is so mean.
He made me work on the weekends.
That company is so terrible.
I mean, that kind of
stuff no one wants to hear.
- Yeah, exactly, and I
think it's not really useful
because even if the
company is the competitor,
so you're not really getting
the extra points for giving them
like the dirty secrets of what
was going on in the company,
maybe saying, oh, my co-workers, they were
just so mean to me and stuff like this.
- Yeah, no, it makes you
seem like a complainer
and no one wants
to hire a complainer.
- Exactly.
- All right, so this is an interesting
topic we would like to hear from you.
So, come to Englishpot.com and tell us
why did you leave your previous employer?
- Or just let us know about
some of your interview
experiences or some of
your interview questions.
We're happy to help you out.
We'll hope to see you at the website.
- All right, we'll see you there.
- Bye. - Bye.
(upbeat music)